A Guide to the J. Russell Bailey, Records, 1935-1986
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
J. Russell Bailey, Records, 1935-1986
The Library of Virginia
38513
5.7 cu. ft.
J. Russell Bailey
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Barbara B. McBride, Northfield, IL, 9 October 2001.
Biographical Information
J. Russell Bailey (1905-1998) was born in Southampton, New York, on October 19, 1905. He studied architecture at the University of Michigan and at the Cranbrook Academy of Art in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan. At Cranbrook, the young architect studied in the first class taught by architect Eliel Saarinen. Bailey's designs for the developement of Mantauk Point, Long Island, New York, from that time period were published in the Architectural Record in 1933. Needing to associate himself with a more established architect because of the on-going economic depression, Bailey joined the firm of Arthur H. Newman from 1933 until just prior to World War II. It was at that time that he joined the Architectural Section of the United States Coast Guard. There, he first ventured into library design with his work on the United States Coast Guard Library in New London, Connecticut.
After military service, Bailey was asked to join manufacturer and architect Angus Snead McDonald in a venture that included designing library buildings. McDonald was head of the well-known Snead and Company firm which manufactured multi-tiered bookshelves for libraries around the world. Modular designs for library buildings were coming into vogue and McDonald and his company had a great impact on their use. In 1946, Bailey resigned from Snead and Company to form his own practice in Orange, Virginia.
Under McDonald's supervision, Bailey had become proponent of modular design in library planning. Throughout his career, he consulted on or designed a significant number of university, college, private, and public library buildings utilizing this design theory. J. Russell Bailey's commissions include Yale University, University of Virginia, University of Maryland, Medical College of Virginia, Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, Beloit College, and University of Georgia, to mention a few. As his office became more prolific, Bailey took on a partner, Judson M. Gardner, and the firm became known as Bailey and Gardner, Architects. Eventually, the firm was renamed Bailey Gardner and Gillum Architects.
J. Russell Bailey died at his home in Orange, Virginia, on May 28, 1998, at the age of 92.
Scope and Content
This accession consists of the surviving office and project files of J. Russell Bailey, principal in the architectural firm of Bailey and Gardner and well-known library building designer. The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, clippings, photographs, facsimiles, drawings, sketches, and renderings. Series have been designated for Office Records and Project Records. All project-specific materials are included in Series II: Project Records. All general materials, such as clippings not related to a specific project, are housed in Series I: Office Files. This arrangement was imposed by the records' creator(s) and maintained by the processing archivist.
Series I: Office Files, 1935-1986, contains mainly general correspondence, publicity materials, and writings and speeches by J. Russell Bailey. Biographical data on Bailey can also be found in this series.
Series II: Project Files, 1938-1981, consists of project-specific correspondence, publicity and construction photographs, publications, drawings, renderings, sketches, notes, and memoranda. The projects are arranged alphabetically by name. No differentiation has been made between the architect's consulting projects and those in which he was sole or collaborative designer.
Arrangement
Arranged by series number and alphabetically by folder title there under.
Contents List
- Office Files 1935-1986
  Arrangement: Alphabetical by folder title.
  - Biographical Data, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, General, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, General, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, General, 1952-1955, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, General, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, J. Russell Bailey, ca. 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Publicity Materials, 1947-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Speeches and Writings, J. Russell Bailey, 1935-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speeches and Writings, J. Russell Bailey, 1963-1969, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Project Files, 1938-1981
  - Alexandria Public Library, Ellen Coolidge Burke Branch (VA), ca. 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny College (PA), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alliance Chapel (PA), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Appalachian State University (NC), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Arlington Public Library, Central Branch (VA), 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Arlington Public Library, Central Branch (VA), ca. 1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    OVERSIZE materials.
  - Arlington Public Library, Cherrydale Branch (VA), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Arlington Public Library, Glencarlyn Branch (VA), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Arlington Public Library, Shirlington Branch, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Arlington Public Library, Westover Branch (VA), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Austin Seminary (TX), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Beloit College (WI), 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Berkeley Divinity School (CT), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Botetourt-Rockbridge Regional Library (VA), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bridgewater College (VA), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Carter, Claiborne B. (VA), 1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Citadel, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Concordia College (IL), ca. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Converse College (SC), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Covington-Alleghany Library (VA), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Danville Public Library (VA), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Davidson College (NC), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - DePauw University (IN), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Eastern Mennonite College (VA), 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Elkhart Public Library (IN), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Emory University (GA), 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Emory and Henry College (VA), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Falls Church Library (VA), 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Falls Church Library (VA), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Falls Church Library (VA), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Falls Church Library (VA), 1958, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Headquarters (VA), ca. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Headquarters (VA), ca. 1962 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Richard Byrd Branch (VA), ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Thomas Jefferson Branch (VA), 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Dolly Madison Branch (VA), 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, George Mason Branch (VA), ca. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Sherwood Reference Center (VA), 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Martha Washington Branch (VA), 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fairfax Co. Public Library, Woodrow Wilson Branch (VA), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Goldsboro-Wayne Co. Public Library (NC), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gordonsville Community Hospital (VA), 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gordonsville Community Hospital (VA), 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gordonsville Motor Court (VA), 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Institute of Textile Technology (VA), 1938-1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Institute of Textile Technology (VA), 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Institute of Textile Technology (VA), 1955, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Institute of Textile Technology (VA), 1947 (Map-case 4-G-8, Drawer 3)
  - Jefferson-Madison Public Library, Gordon Ave. Branch (VA), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Kentucky Flooring (VA), ca. 1946 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Kentucky Flooring (VA), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Kenyon College (OH), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Louisa Baptist Church (VA), 1954 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Louisa High School (VA), 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Madison Co. Courthouse (VA), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Madison Co. Courthouse (VA), 1952 (Map-case 4-G-8, Drawer 3)
  - Marshall Terrace (VA), 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mary Baldwin College (VA), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Mercer University (GA), 1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Mississippi State University (MS), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - NAHB-Forum House Design Competition, n.d. (Map-case 4-G-8, Drawer 3)
  - Orange Baptist Church (VA), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Orange Co. Historical Society (VA), 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Orange Co. Historical Society (VA), 1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Orange Co. Nursing Home (VA), 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Orange Co. Nursing Home (VA), 1980-1981 (Map-case 4-G-8, Drawer 3)
  - Orange Co. Public Library (VA), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Orange Presbyterian Church (VA), 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Parkersburg and Wood Cos. Public Libraries (WV), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Presbyterian Colleges (SC), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary (a.k.a. Virginia Theological Seminary)(VA), 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary (a.k.a. Virginia Theological Seminary)(VA), 1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary (a.k.a. Virginia Theological Seminary)(VA), Jan. 1956 - Jly. 1956 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary (a.k.a. Virginia Theological Seminary)(VA), Aug. 1956 - Jan. 1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary (a.k.a. Virginia Theological Seminary)(VA), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary (a.k.a. Virginia Theological Seminary) (VA), 1955 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Randolph-Macon College (VA), 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Randolph-Macon Women's College (VA), 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Randolph-Macon Women's College (VA), 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Richmond Public Library (VA), ca. 1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Roberts Wesleyan College (NY), 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Robeson Co. Public Library (NC), 1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - South Boston Public Library (VA), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - South Carolina State Library (SC), 1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Snead and Co. Houses, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Sweetbriar College (VA), 1964-1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Thomas Nelson Community College (VA), 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Union Theological Seminary (VA), 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Union Theological Seminary (VA), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - University of North Carolina (NC), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - University of North Dakota (ND), 1961 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - University of Richmond, Boatwright Library (VA), 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - University of Richmond, Boatwright Library (VA), 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - University of Richmond, Chapel (VA), 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - University of Virginia, Alderman Library (VA), 1969-1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - University of Virginia, Alderman Library (VA), 1976-1977 (Map-case 4-G-8, Drawer 3)
  - University of Virginia, Health Sciences Library (VA), 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Drawings, n.d. (Map-case 4-G-8, Drawer 3)
  - Unidentified Recreation Building, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute (VA), 1949-1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Washington College (MD), 1967-1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Washington College (MD), 1967-1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Waynesboro Public Library (VA), 1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Wesleyan Campus (GA), 1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Westminster Theological Seminary (PA), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Woodberry Forest (VA), 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 10)